Guide to the Brown, Clawson, and Parvin family fapers 1739-1978
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Brown, Clawson, and Parvin family papers
1739-1978
1885-1941
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Brown, Clawson and Parvin families
Mss 2506
1 cubic feet (1 document case, 1 oversize folder)
Papers of the families of the Brown, Clawson, and Parvin families of Oregon, including materials related to composer and music teacher Zimiri Mullin Parvin (1845-1921), his daughter Mamie Parvin Brown, his grandson Vivian Z. Brown, and Vivian's wife Verne Clawson Brown. Includes correspondence, documents, clippings, and ephemera.
Zimiri Parvin Brown was a composer and professor of music who lived in Salem and Portland, Oregon during the latter part of his life. He was born in Ripley County, Indiana in 1843, served in the Civil War in 64th and 151st Illinois Infantry, and married Addie Sutton in 1866. He studied music from 1868 to 1874, and became the director of music at the State Normal School of California (now San Jose State University) in 1875. In 1883 he was appointed Dean of the College of Music at Willamette University in Salem, Oregon, a post he held until his move to Portland in 1906. He was also director of the Albany Conservatory of Music in Albany, Oregon. In Portland he helped to found the Northwestern Normal School of Music and Art. He was an expert on harmony and published many compositions including The wide world knows the Portland Rose.
In 1890, Zimiri Parvin's daughter Mamie married James Nassau Brown (1857-1912), a Portland attorney. Brown was the son of Martin Brown (1809-1902) and Susan Jane Goddard Brown (1819-1868). He was a native of Iowa and lived in Missouri and Idaho before graduating from Willamette University Law School in 1888. He practiced law in Heppner, Oregon, served in the Oregon State Legislature from 1893-1898, and later established a law practice in Portland and Salem.
A son of James and Mamie Brown, Vivian Z. Brown, became a dentist in the U. S. Army Dental Corps. He graduated from Portland's Lincoln High School in 1911 and from North Pacific College in 1917. In that year he married Verne Clawson (b. 1889), the daughter of Walter and Nella Clawson. She had graduated from Portland's Washington High School in 1910 and attended the Northwest Normal School of Music and Art. Vivian Brown became an officer in the U.S. Army Dental Corps in the 1920s and was promoted to Colonel during World War II. Among his children was Walter Zimiri Brown (b. 1922).
The collection includes correspondence, clippings, documents, and ephemera, most of which relate to Zimiri Parvin, James Nassau Brown, Mamie Parvin Brown, Vivian Z. Brown, and Verne Clawson Brown. There are also some materials on the Sutton, Taylor, and Price families, all related by marriage to the Parvins and Browns. Included are: musical compositions by Zimiri Parvin, letters from James Nassau Brown to his wife Mamie, a biographical article by Doris Huffman (1976), diplomas and certificates, high school yearbooks, a pocket diary of Josephine Taylor Sutton containing recipes, a program for a banquet honoring Susan B. Anthony in Salem in 1900, a Taylor family history document from the late 18th century, a group of baggage tags from hotels, and a collection of bank notes from the early 19th century. Among James Nassau Brown's letters is one of 1903 from Salem describing a typhoid epidemic.
The collection is arranged in the following series: Series A: Brown family, general, 1896-1978; Series B: Zimiri Mullin Parvin materials, 1860-1976; Series C: Other family members, 1739-1941.
Collection is open for research.
Gifts of Colonel and Mrs. Walter Zimiri Brown, 1978 August, Library Accession 14550 and Museum Accession 78-64; and Mr. and Mrs. John Parvin, 1991 July, Library Accession 20363.
Photographs acquired with this collection were separated to photograph collections, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
Artifacts acquired with this collection are now housed in the Artifact Collection, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Brown, James Nassau--Correspondence; Brown, Mamie Parvin--Correspondence; Brown, Verne Clawson; Brown, Vivian Z; Brown, Walter Zimiri; Huffman, Doris; Parvin, Zimiri Mullin, 1845-1921
Brown family; Clawson family; Parvin family; Sutton family; Taylor family
Albany Conservatory of Music (Albany, Or.); Lincoln High School (Portland, Or.); Northwestern Normal School of Music and Art (Portland, Or.); Washington High School (Portland, Or.); Willamette University
Portland (Or.)--History; Portland (Or.)--Social life and customs; Salem (Or.)--History; Salem (Or.)--Social life and customs; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Music--Oregon--History; Typhoid fever--Oregon--Salem--History
Colleges and Universities; Home and Family; Oregon; Performing Arts; Portland; Women
genealogies; invitations; letters; paper money; school yearbooks; tags
Brown, James Nassau; Parvin, Zimiri Mullin, 1845-1921
Brown family; Clawson family; Parvin family
Souvenir program from banquet in honor of Susan B. Anthony is viewable online in OHS Digital Collections.
- Brown family, general, 1896-1978; Series A
  - Inventory to Accession 14550, circa 1978 (Folder 1)
  - Brown family genealogical information, 1934; undated (Folder 2)
  - Brown, Parvin, Sutton families--Death notices, clippings, 1896-1921 (Folder 3)
- Zimiri Mullin Parvin materials, 1860-1922; Series B
  - Zimiri Parvin letters, 1901; 1904; undated (Folder 4)
  - Military papers, circa 1860; 1921-1922 (Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1903-1921 (Folder 6)
  - Programs for recitals and other events, Normal College of Music, Portland, and Northwestern School of Music and Art, Portland, 1910-1921 (Folder 7)
  - Sheet music, programs, and birthday speech, 1889-1914 (Folder 8)
  - Sheet music for Thine eyes shall see the king, Do you want any stars in your crown, and The whole word knows the Portland rose, 1906; undated (Folder 9)
  - Doris Huffman, "The music 'doc' of Willamette", 1976 (Folder 10)
  - "Dr. Parvin's anniversary occasion" (typescript), 1914 April 25 (Folder 11)
  - Harmony works by Parvin, 1915; undated (Folder 12)
  - Original lyrics by Parvin, undated (Folder 13)
- Other family members, 1739-1941; Series C
  - James Nassau Brown papers
    - Letters to Mamie, 1886-1894 (Folder 14)
    - Letters to Mamie, 1894-1903 (Folder 15)
    - Letter to Lillie la Munyon regarding typhoid fever, 1903 (Folder 16)
    - Letters to Mamie, 1904 Aug-1909 (Folder 17)
    - Letter to Vivian Brown, 1904 July 14 (Folder 18)
    - Letters to Mamie, 1904 July (Folder 19)
    - Teacher's certificate, 1885 October 13 (Folder 20)
    - Lillia la Munyon correspondence, 1899-1902 (Folder 21)
  - Vivian Z. Brown papers
    - Commencement announcement and other documents, 1934; 1938 (Folder 22)
    - Invitations, programs, and other ephemera, 1926-1933 (Folder 23)
    - Letters, 1901; 1933; undated (Folder 24)
    - Lincoln High School yearbook, 1911 (Folder 25)
    - Walter Zimiri Brown--Birth and graduation announcements, 1922; 1941 (Folder 26)
    - Walter Zimiri Brown letters, 1932; 1960 (Folder 27)
    - William and Susan Burns Carroll letters to Della Carroll Clawson Hartness, 1908-1909 (Folder 28)
    - Marriage certificate of Adelbert T. Harness and Della B. Clawson, 1914 (Folder 29)
    - Grace Clawson Hostetter, letter regarding grandmother's death, 1900 (Folder 30)
    - Matilda Jamieson letters to Nancy L. Clawson, 1904; 1907 (Folder 31)
    - Pension certificate for Addie Parvin, 1922 (Folder 32)
    - Grace Clawson Hostetter letters to Mary L. Clawson Price, and telegram to Grace Hostetter, 1905-1907 (Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, W. H. Clawson, Nancy C. Price, 1895-1912 (Folder 34)
    - Song lyrics sent to Nancy L. Clawson, undated (Folder 35)
  - Verne Clawson papers
    - Verne Clawson birth certificate and graduation program announcement, 1906; 1910 (Folder 36)
    - Marriage announcement, Verne Clawson and Vivian Brown, 1917 (Folder 37)
    - Graduation announcement, yearbook, souvenir, Washington High School, 1910 (Folder 38)
    - Addie Sutton Parvin letters, 1903-1904 (Folder 39)
    - Addie Sutton Parvin correspondence with Mamie Brown, 1923-1926 (Folder 40)
    - Josephine Taylor Sutton diary with recipes, 1872 (Folder 41)
    - W. P. Taylor letter to Addie Sutton Parvin, 1898 (Folder 42)
    - Alexander B. Price and Mary L. Price--Awards, complaint, and summons, 1917 (Folder 43)
    - Sutton family agreement, 1891 (Folder 44)
    - Susan B. Anthony banquet program and other ephemera, 1889-1909 (Folder 45)
    - Luggage tags, undated (Folder 46)
    - Paper money, including "fractional currency", 1824; 1829 (Folder 47)
    - Diplomas and certificates, 1739-1941 (Folder Oversize)
      Includes manuscript music by Zimiri Parvin to "A piece of pumpkin pie"; Taylor family birth and death document, 1739-1860.